Finding Aid for Save Our Sons and Daughters (Organization) records, 1987-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Save Our Sons and Daughters (Organization) records 1987-1992
Save Our Sons and Daughters (Organization)
2 linear feet
921104 Bj 2
Detroit-based civic organization (known as SOSAD) formed to educated the public to the problem of teen violence and youth homicide. Topical files, correspondence, and videotape relating to organizational programs and activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred by the organization (Donor No. 8032 ) in May 1992.
The record group is open to research.
Save Our Sons and Daughters (SOSAD) was organized in 1987 by Clementine Barfield, who currently serves as its executive director. In January of that year, Ms. Barfield called together several parents of children killed in Detroit during 1986. Her son Derick Barfield was killed in July 1986 and another son critically wounded. The parents and concerned citizens met at the Church of the New Covenant-Baptist to organize a support group and to fight for gun control. They designated themselves "The Group Without A Name" (GWN).
The first act of the newly formed group was to declare a week of prayer in memory of the deceased youth. The week culminated with a memorial service on February 8, 1987, at the cathedral of St. Paul's in Detroit, and was attended by over 1,400 people. This memorial service has become a yearly tradition with SOSAD. In the aftermath of the memorial service over 300 people attended a meeting with Barfield and others from GWN on February 15, 1987 to form an organization. In late March the organization officially took the name SOSAD.
Since its founding, SOSAD has conducted and planned many community programs aimed at reducing youth homicides in Detroit and addressing the problem of teen violence. These programs include a 24 hour telephone hotline to support survivors of violence; youth leadership classes; grief counseling; crisis intervention programs in area schools; a speakers bureau to address community organizations, schools, churches and legislators; and a court watching system to assist families going through the criminal justice system. In providing support for survivors, SOSAD conducts a grief counseling session every week for the parents and relatives of children who have been killed. The organization has also undertaken marches in Detroit to stop violence and holds an anti-handgun vigil every Monday at noon in downtown Detroit. Financial support for SOSAD comes from government funds, foundation grants, proceeds from benefits, membership dues, and donations from supporters. Branches of SOSAD are being organized in other cities including Flint, Michigan; Fresno, California; St. Louis, Missouri; Birmingham, Alabama; and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Clementine Barfield was born and raised in the Mississippi Delta. She received her BS degree from Wayne State University in 1981, and an honorary doctorate from Marygrove College (Detroit, Michigan) in 1988. She has received many awards from local and national organizations for her work in the areas of violence prevention, victim advocacy and community service, including an award from President Ronald Reagan during Crime Victim Awareness Week in 1988. She has appeared on a number of national television programs such as Oprah Winfrey, Phil Donahue, Geraldo Rivera, and 20/20, and her work has been featured in national publications such as Ms, magazine (1991) and Women's World. In addition to her work with SOSAD, Ms. Barfield has served as board member of the National Organization of Victim Assistance (NOVA), co-chair of the Detroit Spotlight Crime Task Force, and member of the Wayne County Crime Reduction Advisory Board.
The records of Save Our Sons and Daughters comprise two linear feet. The records are divided into three series: Topical Files, Correspondence, and Visual. The collection is most valuable for the documentation it provides on the establishment and life of an urban, grass roots organization. It also provides insight into the profound impact of teen violence on the lives of Detroiters.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.); Murder--Michigan--Detroit.; Juvenile delinquency--Michigan--Detroit.; Save Our Sons and Daughters (Organization); Violence in children.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Detroit (Mich.); Juvenile delinquents.; Save Our Sons and Daughters (Organization); Violence.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Topical Files 1987-1992
  The Topical Files series (1 linear foot) is arranged alphabetically. The materials in the Background and Bylaws files and the paper SOSAD: The Emergence of an Organization to Stop Kids Killing Kids in Detroit, provide the best overview of the history of the organization and its goals and activities. The Activities files are primarily comprised of publicity materials from marches, rallies, and benefits, and transcripts from hearings and workshops. Matters of funding, policy, and administration are documented in the Financial Records and Grant Materials files and in the Minutes from various SOSAD committees, although the runs of the latter are incomplete. The Counseling files provide a very good introduction to those services. The Youth Programs folder contains descriptions of SOSAD programs in peer counseling, conflict resolution, substance abuse prevention and urban farming (Harvest '88). The Questionnaires were handed out to persons attending their first SOSAD meeting and ask about the effects of teen violence on the attendees lives, possible solutions to the problem, and activities they think SOSAD should concentrate on. There is an incomplete run of the SOSAD newsletter, which is an important means of sending the organization's message out to the community and of gathering support. The newsletters include notices of programs and activities, writings by SOSAD members, and information on the work of other groups with concerns similar to those of SOSAD.
  Other materials in the Topical Files series unrelated to the day-to-day affairs of SOSAD but nonetheless interesting, include the Collected Materials files of documents from various organizations to which Ms. Barfield devoted her time, and the Children's Essays on Peace written by children (probably grade school) on how to have peace without fighting. The P.E.O.P.L.E.'s Platform is a statement of the group's principles and includes discussion of problems facing Detroit and strategies for coping with them.
  The Children's Death Listings, Children's Essays on Peace, and Questionnaires from the Topical series, the chronological subseries of Correspondence and letters from Incarcerated Youth in the topical subseries, and Stop the Madness all provide poignant documentation of the effects of violence, or the threat of it, on the lives of people living in Detroit.
  - Activities
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - Arms Around the Children Campaign 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Background Materials 1986, 1992 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws undated (Box 1)
  - Central Valley SOSAD (Fresno, CA) 1991 (Box 1)
  - Children's Death Statistics undated (Box 1)
  - Children's Essays on Peace 1990 (Box 1)
  - Collected Materials
    - The Children and Youth Initiative of Detroit/Wayne County (Box 1)
    - City of Detroit City Council Youth Advisory Commission 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Strategic Plan Crime Task Force 1987 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Detroit Metropolitan Area 1987-1990 (Box 1)
      - Lansing Metropolitan Area 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - P.E.O.P.L.E.'s Party Platform (Detroit) 1989 (People for Empowerment, Openness, Principled Leadership, and Excellence in Government) (Box 1)
    - Project Start (Detroit) (Service Together And Rehabilitation Together)
      - Background Materials (Box 1)
      - Board of Directors Minutes 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Counseling
    - Handouts undated (Box 1)
    - Programs undated (Box 1)
    - Student Therapists 1990 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    (includes balance sheets, income statements, budgets)
  - Fundraising "Plan-of-Action," 1989 (Box 1)
  - Grant Materials
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Brunch December, 1990, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Services 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - Economics Committee 1988 (Box 1)
    - Executive Board 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - General Membership 1987-1989, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Social Issues Committee 1987 (Box 1)
    - Staff Meetings September 28, 1990-January 15, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Steering Committee 1987-1991 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1987-1992 (Box 1)
  - Proposal to Add Three New Programs to the Existing Youth Programs of SOSAD undated (Box 1)
  - Questionnaires undated (Box 1)
  - SOSAD: The Emergence of an Organization to Stop Kids Killing Kids in Detroit, 1989 (by Mary Lou Dietz and S. Rani Dronamraju, University of Windsor, presented at the North Central Sociological Association Meeting) (Box 1)
  - Testimony of SOSAD to U.S. House Subcommittee on Criminal Justice December 11, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Youth Programs 1988-1990 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1987-1992
  The Correspondence series (1 linear foot) is arranged in two subseries, chronological and topical. The chronological correspondence dates from the founding of SOSAD in 1987 to 1992. For the years 1987-1989, the correspondence is mostly incoming. The years 1990-1991 include both incoming and outgoing correspondence. There is only one letter, soliciting funds, for 1992. Much of the correspondence concerns administration of the various activities of SOSAD, but there are also moving letters of support and encouragement. In the topical subseries there are incoming and outgoing letters for Ms. Barfield (Barfield, Personal) which were kept separate from the rest of the correspondence by the SOSAD staff. Some of the letters are related to SOSAD activities, others are of a more personal nature. There are very interesting letters from Incarcerated Youth from around the state, who write about their lives in prison and their support for the work of SOSAD. The letters also include scattered issues of inmate newsletters from various prisons. The Patricia Bondy correspondence is mostly outgoing and provides routine information on SOSAD counseling programs.
  - 1987 (Box 2)
  - 1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1989, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1990
    - outgoing (Box 2)
    - incoming (Box 2)
  - 1991
    - outgoing (Box 2)
    - incoming (Box 2)
  - 1992 (Box 2)
  - Barfield, Personal 1987-1990 (Box 2)
  - Bondy, Patricia (Bereavement Counselor, outgoing correspondence) 1990 (Box 2)
  - Form Letters undated (Box 2)
  - Incarcerated Youth (incoming correspondence from) 1990-1991 (Box 2)
- Visual
  The Visual series contains one videotape. The tape includes Stop the Madness, a 34 minute documentary filmed on the streets of Detroit which discusses the nature and causes of teen violence in the city and explores the origins of SOSAD. Stop the Madness was produced and directed by Jerome Thomas in 1989. The videotape also contains Fire in Their Hearts, a brief documentary on the work of SOSAD, much of which is similar to Stop the Madness. Brief footage from local news coverage of a SOSAD New Years Eve Memorial Service is also included on the tape.
  - Videotape (VHS): includes Stop the Madness, 1989 news footage of New Years Eve Memorial Service, WDIV-Detroit, December 1990, and Fire in Their Hearts, 1990 (Box 2)
    (DVD use copy available)